Guide to the Burton Kendall Wheeler papers 1910-1972
Montana Historical Society
- Press Releases
  - re Railroad Reorganization Act (S 2009); Seaboard Company, Ltd.; federal guarantee of bank deposits; U.S. Reclamation Service; drought in Montana; Gerald P. Nye; the Flathead Project; William Leahy; American workers; seed loans to farmers on relief; 73rd Congress, undated (Box-folder 8 / 12)
- Photographs
  - List of photographs transferred to the Photo Archives (Box-folder 8 / 13)
- Printed Material
  - "Indian Affairs: Letters of Commissioner" (re land allotments, liens upon Indian lands, tribal claims pending before Commission, and irrigation of Indian lands), 1929 (Box-folder 8 / 14)
  - Bimetallism (includes "Independent Bimetallism or Bolschevism?" by Jonathan Bourne, Jr.; "The Silver Question: Elementary Facts Bearing on the Silver Question" by Joel F. Vaile, 1896, 1896, 1932-1933 (Box-folder 8 / 15)
  - "Brief on Peace-Time Military Conscription" submitted by Lawyers Committee to Keep the United States Out of War, circa 1940 (Box-folder 8 / 16)
  - Congressional Record reprints re B.K. Wheeler, 1924-1959 (Box-folder 8 / 17-18)
  - Democratic Party, 1932-1940 (Box-folder 8 / 19)
  - Jerry O'Connell for Congress, 1938 (Box-folder 8 / 20)
  - List of printed material transferred to the Library (Box-folder 8 / 21)
  - "Report of the Official Canvass of the Vote Cast at the Primary Election Held in the State of Montana, July 21, 1936" (annotated with Jerry O'Connell votes, July 19, 1938) (Box-folder 8 / OvFd)
  - "Rules of the Municipal Court for the District of Columbia", 1950 (Box-folder 8 / 22)
  - Supreme Court reorganization, 1937 (Box-folder 8 / 23-24)
  - U.S. House Judiciary Committee inquiry into the conduct of Harry M. Daugherty: adverse report and minority views, January 1923 (Box-folder 8 / 25)
  - U.S. Senate Select Committee on the Investigation of the Attorney General, hearings Vol. 1-3 (re Harry M. Daugherty and Teapot Dome scandal), March-June 1924 (Box-folder 9 / 1-2)
  - U.S. Senate Select Committee on Interstate Commerce: To Prevent Uniform Delivered Prices, hearings, March-April 1936 (Box-folder 9 / 3)
  - U.S. Senate Committee on Interstate Commerce: Investigation of Railroads, Holding Companies, and Affiliated Companies: preliminary report (re MidAmerica Corporation), March 1937 (Box-folder 9 / 4)
  - U.S. Senate Subcommittee of the Committee on Interstate Commerce: Investigation of Railroads, Holding Companies, and Affiliated Companies: hearings, parts 1-10, December 1936- October 1937 (Box-folder 10 / 1-5)
  - U.S. Senate Subcommittee of the Committee on Interstate Commerce: Investigation of Railroads, Holding Companies, and Affiliated Companies: hearings, parts 11-22, October 1937- March 1938 (Box-folder 11 / 1-6)
  - U.S. Senate Subcommittee of the Committee on Interstate Commerce: Investigation of Railroads, Holding Companies, and Affiliated Companies: hearings, parts 23-29, March 1938- 1942 (Box-folder 12 / 1-3)
  - U.S. Senate Subcommittee of the Committee on Interstate Commerce: Investigation of Railroads, Holding Companies, and Affiliated Companies: report no. 25, parts 1-27, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 12 / 4)
  - U.S. Senate Subcommittee of the Committee on Interstate Commerce: Investigation of Railroads, Holding Companies, and Affiliated Companies: report no. 1182 parts 1-2, 1940 (Box-folder 12 / 5)
  - U.S. Senate Subcommittee of the Committee on Interstate Commerce: Investigation of Railroads, Holding Companies, and Affiliated Companies: report no. 1182 parts 3-5, 1940 (Box-folder 13 / 1-2)
  - U.S. Senate Subcommittee of the Committee on Interstate Commerce: Investigation of Railroads, Holding Companies, and Affiliated Companies: report no. 26 parts 1-2, 1941 (Box-folder 13 / 3)
  - U.S. Senate Subcommittee of the Committee on Interstate Commerce: Investigation of Railroads, Holding Companies, and Affiliated Companies: report no. 714 parts 1-4, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 13 / 4-5)
  - "War and Labor Voting Records: U.S. Congress 1937-1941" compiled and published by Congressional Intelligence, 1942 (Box-folder 14 / 1)
  - B.K. Wheeler, circa 1925- 1944, undated (Box-folder 14 / 2)
  - World War II [additional material in Oversize Folder], 1940-1942 (Box-folder 14 / 3)
  - Miscellaneous government publications, 1936-1942 (Box-folder 14 / 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1938-1969 (Box-folder 14 / 5)
  - "An Answer to the Testimony in Behalf of the President's Plan" (re reorganization of the Supreme Court: includes index, text, and exhibits; some material in Oversize Folder), circa 1937 (Box-folder 14 / 6-10)
- Speeches
  - "The Building of a Nation" (re American politics), 1923 (Box-folder 15 / 1)
  - Address before the laymen of the Methodist Conference at City Club, Boston (excerpts, re the economy), January 1924 (Box-folder 15 / 2)
  - Speeches made during the LaFollette-Wheeler campaign, 1924 (Box-folder 15 / 3)
  - "Child Labor Amendment", 1925 (Box-folder 15 / 4)
  - re Robert M. Lafollette, Sr.; Robert M. LaFollette, Jr., 1925 (Box-folder 15 / 5)
  - "Irresponsible Autocracy" (re Coolidge administration); "It Is Time to Call a Halt" (re Indians' right to sue the federal government); "Long-and-Short-Haul Clause of Interstate Commerce Act"; "Reply to Commissioner Burke's Accusations"; "What the Progressive Farmers of the South Think of the McNary-Haugen Bill"; "What is Back of the So-Called Administration Farm Bill" (re farm prices, agriculture), 1926 (Box-folder 15 / 6)
  - re Nicaragua; "Farm Relief", 1927 (Box-folder 15 / 7)
  - "Concessions in Foreign Countries"; "Why Are We in Nicaragua?"; "Pullman Surcharge"; "Railroad Rates on Agricultural Products"; "Campaign Expenditures"; "Mexican Situation", 1928 (Box-folder 15 / 8)
  - "Farm Relief Bill"; "Federal Farm Board"; "Grundy Appointment"; "Grundyism"; Senator Brookhart's re-election, 1929 (Box-folder 15 / 9)
  - "What the Progressive Democrats and Republicans Are Fighting for in Congress"; "The Rayon Industry and the Tariff"; "Muscle Shoals and the Power Question"; national parks; monopolies; Smoot-Hawley Tariff; "The Trend from Democracy to Autocracy" (re government by commissions and bureaus), 1930 (Box-folder 15 / 10)
  - "What the Nation Needs"; "The Farm Problem"; "Lobbying"; the Balkan situation; power rates' Tom Moody pardon, 1931 (Box-folder 15 / 11)
  - "Remonetization of Silver"; "Money and the Price Level"; "Muscle Shoals and the Power Question"; Thomas Jefferson, 1932 (Box-folder 15 / 12)
  - Franklin D. Roosevelt nomination; National Farmers' Union; "The United States and Europe", 1932 (Box-folder 15 / 13)
  - "Remonetization of Silver"; "Dishonest Bankers"; "Silver Money"; "The Silver Question"; "Inflation"; "Bimetallism", 1933 (Box-folder 15 / 14)
  - "The Five Year Plan" (re Soviet Union); "Will of the West"; "Great Lakes-St. Lawrence Treaty"; St. Patrick's Day address; silver remonetization, 1934 (Box-folder 16 / 1)
  - "World Court"; "Government Ownership of Railroads"; "Public Utility Holding Company Bill"; "The Real Red Menace" (re public utility holding companies); "Issues Before America" (re corporations); "Interstate Bus Control"; interest rates and the farm depression; silver remonetization, 1935 (Box-folder 16 / 2)
  - "Consumer Cooperatives"; "Cooperatives in Rural Electrification"; problems posed by the Depression; "Railroads' Problems Today", 1936 (Box-folder 16 / 3)
  - Senate campaign speeches, 1936 (Box-folder 16 / 4)
  - Investigation of agricultural income and the financial and economic condition of agricultural producers; "What Is the Most Important Issue Before the American People Today?"; "America Must Choose"; water conservation; Wheeler-Rayburn Holding Company Act, 1936 (Box-folder 16 / 5)
  - Reorganization of the Supreme Court, 1937 (Box-folder 16 / 6-8)
  - "The Interstate Commerce Act and the Interstate Commerce Commission from the Standpoint of the United States Senate"; "What Congress Can Do Now on Taxation"; "Naziism vs. Americanism"; executive reorganization; U.S. Constitution, 1937 (Box-folder 16 / 9)
  - "Railroad Situation Today"; regulation of broadcasting; waste in railroad industry; "Transportation Outlook", 1938 (Box-folder 17 / 1)
  - "Statement on the Big Navy Bill"; "W.P.A. and Politics"; "Reorganization of Executive Departments"; "The Silver Policy"; speech to United Palestine Appeal; "False Statements of Congressman Jerry O'Connell", 1938 (Box-folder 17 / 2)
  - "Foreign Policy and Neutrality"; "America Must Remain at Peace", 1939 (Box-folder 17 / 3)
  - "Farm-Mortgage Refinancing"; Wheeler homecoming, 1939 (Box-folder 17 / 4)
  - National issues; agricultural legislation; "A Liberal Looks at Private Enterprise"; speech to National Association of Manufacturers; neutrality and the national economy, 1939 (Box-folder 17 / 5)
  - "Present Railroad Problems"; "Our Transportation Problem"; "How Can We Solve the Railroad Problem"; "Railroad Problems and Their Relief", 1939 (Box-folder 17 / 6)
  - "Keep Out of War"; nomination of Henry L. Stimson and Frank Knox; "The Dangers of Peacetime Conscription with Democracy"; "Is Peace Time Conscription Consonant with Democracy?"; "Peacetime Conscription"; "Let's Go to War Now: an Answer"; "Conscription and National Defense"; "Our Foreign Policy"; "A Just Peace"; "Should the United States Urge a Negotiated Peace Now?", 1940 (Box-folder 17 / 7)
  - Andrew Jackson; transportation legislation; United Mine Workers; Abraham Lincoln; railroad problem; "Government Control of Business"; "1940 Liberalism"; neutrality (Box-folder 17 / 8)
  - Railroad legislation; "The Railroads and Economic Conditions Confronting the Country"; farm appropriations legislation; "The Relief Problem"; "Youth: Jobs and War", 1940 (Box-folder 17 / 9)
  - Neutrality speech on NBC Radio Network (phonograph records], circa 1940 (Box-folder 18 / 1-4)
  - Neutrality; "The Lend-Lease Bill Means War"; "Lend-Lease Bill"; "America, You Will Love War!"; "The Bill 1776: The Road to War"; "Unity for Peace"; "Convoy of Supplies Means War"; "Peace", 1941 (Box-folder 19 / 1)
  - HB 1776; neutrality; "The American Enabling Act of 1941"; "War or Peace"; "America First Tribute" (Box-folder 19 / 2)
  - Neutrality; modification of neutrality act, 1941 (Box-folder 19 / 3)
  - Neutrality; "Participation by the United States in War", 1941 (Box-folder 19 / 4)
  - Neutrality; "Tribute to Senator Hiram Johnson", 1941 (Box-folder 19 / 5)
  - Neutrality; "Prevent War by Fighting for Peace", 1941 (Box-folder 19 / 6)
  - Neutrality, 1941 (Box-folder 19 / 7)
  - Senator Murray's accusations, July 1942 (Box-folder 20 / 1)
  - "Let Us Defend the American Home"; "Americanism versus Internationalism in the Post-War Picture"; "The War and the Peace"; "Sound American Policy"; conscription; "To Defer Fathers from Draft"; Senate Resolution 192; planning to win the war, 1943 (Box-folder 20 / 2)
  - "Bases for Permanent Peace"; "The Balance of Power in Europe"; "Our Post War Policy"; "An International Police Force"; "Conditions on the Home Front"; "Artificial Rubber in the Post-War World"; American war aims, 1943 (Box-folder 20 / 3)
  - "Our Dilemma in China"; "Should We Join a World Organization Which May Require Us to Fight to Enforce Its Decisions?"; "World Police Force"; "A People's Peace"; domestic and foreign problems facing post-war Americans, 1944 (Box-folder 20 / 4)
  - "Sound American Policy"; Tyler Kent trial; "Finland"; Atlantic Charter and post-war realities; government in post-war Europe, 1944 (Box-folder 20 / 5)
  - "Our Liberal Heritage"; "The Truth about Fort Peck"; "The Future of Communications"; Senator Nye's re-election; future development of communications industry; "Use of Waters of the Missouri River"; "Freedom of Speech on the Air", 1944 (Box-folder 20 / 6)
  - "The United Nations and Peace"; "Report on European Trip"; "Our Position in Post War", 1945 (Box-folder 20 / 7)
  - "Shall Congress Give Up Its Constitutional Right to Declare War?"; "The Crimea Conference"; "The United Nations Charter"; "American Foreign Policy and Attainment of Peace"; "What Great Britain Can Do to Strengthen her Relations with the United States"; "Universal Military Training"; "America's War and Foreign Policy", 1945 (Box-folder 20 / 8)
  - "Agriculture"; "Much-Maligned American Coal Miners Break All Production Records in 1944", 1945 (Box-folder 20 / 9)
  - Remarks, extensions of remarks, etc. from Congressional Record (includes annotations re speeches of others), Jan-June 1945 (Box-folder 20 / 10)
  - Remarks, extensions of remarks, etc. from Congressional Record (includes annotations re speeches of others), July 1945- June 1946 (Box-folder 21 / 1-2)
  - "The British Loan"; Palestine, 1946 (Box-folder 21 / 3)
  - Primary election campaign, 1946 (Box-folder 21 / 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1947-1959 (Box-folder 21 / 5)
  - Fragments and unidentified, undated (Box-folder 21 / 6)
  - "Addresses and Statements of Hon. B.K. Wheeler", collected by E.B. Craney, 1930-1939 (Box-folder 21 / 7)
  - "Addresses and Statements of Hon. B.K. Wheeler", collected by E.B. Craney [2 vol.], 1940-1946 (Box-folder 22 / 1-2)
- Subject Files
  - J.G. Darden investigation, 1910-1920 (Box-folder 22 / 3)
  - Harry M. Daugherty investigation (re Teapot Dome scandal, etc.) [includes Oversize Folder], 1924-1925 (Box-folder 22 / 4-8)
  - U.S. Justice Department investigations (re McGrain vs. Daugherty), 1920-1925 (Box-folder 23 / 1-5)
  - Wheeler Defense Committee, 1925-1926 (Box-folder 23 / 6)
  - Burton K. Wheeler indictment, 1924-1925 (Box-folder 23 / 7)
- Writings
  - "Why Are We in Nicaragua?"; "Individualism Gains in Russia"; economic demands of farmers; sound money and silver; memo re public utilities, 1927-1932 (Box-folder 23 / 9)
  - "American Points of View", August 1938 (Box-folder 23 / 10)
  - "Memo on Conference at the White House with the President" (re third term), August 1938 (Box-folder 23 / 11)
  - "Railroads on the Witness Stand"; "Shall We Permit Loans to the Allies?"; "America--Gone by Tomorrow?" (re peacetime conscription), 1940 (Box-folder 23 / 12)
  - "The Shocking Truth about Radio", 1944 (Box-folder 23 / 13)
  - "Dangers of Post-War Alliances"; "The Road to Enduring Peace" (re implications of the Atlantic Charter and the United Nations on post-war policies), 1944, 1947 (Box-folder 23 / 14)
  - Transcripts of B.K. Wheeler dictation for autobiography, 1961 (Box-folder 23 / 15)
  - Yankee from the West, early drafts (chapters 1-5), 1961-1962 (Box-folder 23 / 16)
  - Yankee from the West, early drafts (chapters 6-11), 1961-1962 (Box-folder 24 / 1)
  - Yankee from the West, revised drafts, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 24 / 2-4)
  - Yankee from the West, notes, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 24 / 5)
  - "Some of the Devious Paths of the Law", undated (Box-folder 24 / 6)
  - B.K. Wheeler re references to him in Arthur Schlesinger's biography of Franklin D. Roosevelt, undated (Box-folder 24 / 7)
- Miscellany
  - Bills and resolutions introduced by Wheeler, 1933-1938 (Box-folder 24 / 8)
  - Carbon County, Montana, Democratic Central Committee endorsements, August 1932 (Box-folder 24 / 9)
  - Cartoons [photographic copies] used in Cartoons Concerning some Actions of Montana's Senator Burton K. Wheeler, circa 1937- circa 1941 (Box-folder 25 / 1)
  - Ed Craney re European war and discussion of American neutrality on the radio, June 1940 (Box-folder 25 / 2)
  - Edward J. Earley, "Burton Kendall Wheeler and the Election of 1924", undated (Box-folder 25 / 3)
  - Harrison J. Freebourn statements re indictment, 1940 (Box-folder 25 / 4)
  - Hart-Albin strike and B.K. Wheeler, 1939 (Box-folder 25 / 5)
  - List of artifacts transferred to the Museum (Box-folder 25 / 6)
  - "List of Attorneys in Montana Arranged According to Towns", undated (Box-folder 25 / 7)
  - Magazine articles on B.K. Wheeler, 1924-1940, undated (Box-folder 25 / 8)
  - Political materials of others, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 25 / 9)
  - Franklin D. Roosevelt re goals of Administration, 1933 (Box-folder 25 / 10)
  - Richard T. Ruetten's thesis on B.K. Wheeler [fragments], 1961 (Box-folder 25 / 11)
  - Frances Wheeler Sayler's notes, etc. for proposed Wheeler biography, 1951-1956 (Box-folder 25 / 12)
  - Dayton Stoddard manuscript for Wheeler biography [drafts], 1958-1960 (Box-folder 25 / 13-14)
  - Dayton Stoddard manuscript for Wheeler biography [drafts], 1958-1960 (Box-folder 26 / 1-6)
  - U.S. House Special Committee on Un-American Activities subversive investigations materials, 1943 (Box-folder 27 / 1)
  - U.S. State Department news releases, 1943 (Box-folder 27 / 2)
  - Burton K. Wheeler anecdotes re childhood experiences, 1972 (Box-folder 27 / 3)
  - Burton K. Wheeler birthday celebration invitation, 1972 (Box-folder 27 / 4)
  - Burton K. Wheeler diplomatic passport, 1923 (Box-folder 27 / 5)
  - Burton K. Wheeler indictment (speeches by Thomas J. Walsh, W.C. Brown, and J.A. Reed), 1925-1926 (Box-folder 27 / 6)
  - Burton K. Wheeler interview re Thomas J. Walsh [transcript], 1949 (Box-folder 27 / 7)
  - Burton K. Wheeler interview [transcript], 1961 (Box-folder 27 / 8)
  - Burton K. Wheeler interview [transcript], undated (Box-folder 27 / 9)
  - Burton K. Wheeler presidential candidacy endorsements, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 27 / 10)
  - Burton K. Wheeler voting record, 1923-1943 (Box-folder 27 / 11-17)
  - Burton K. Wheeler voting record, 1943-1946 (Box-folder 28 / 1)
  - Burton K. Wheeler voting record on farm issues, 1923-1942 (Box-folder 28 / 2)
  - "Wheeler's Seventeen Years of Voting for Labor", 1940 (Box-folder 28 / 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1931-1945, undated (Box-folder 28 / 4)
- Clippings
  - Butte Miner, 1916 (Box-folder 28 / 5)
  - Butte Bulletin, 1920 (Box-folder 28 / 6)
  - Solidarity, 1920 (Box-folder 28 / 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1922-1924 (Box-folder 28 / 8-11)
  - Burton K. Wheeler indictment, April 1925 (Box-folder 28 / 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1925-1936 (Box-folder 29 / 1-2)
  - Reorganization of the Supreme Court, 1937 (Box-folder 29 / 3)
  - Jerry O'Connell, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 29 / 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 29 / 5)
  - Burton K. Wheeler presidential candidacy, 1939 (Box-folder 29 / 6)
  - Burton K. Wheeler homecoming, Hudson, Massachusetts, 1939 (Box-folder 29 / 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1939 (Box-folder 29 / 8)
  - Harrison Freebourn indictment, 1940 (Box-folder 29 / 9)
  - Burton K. Wheeler senate campaign, 1940 (Box-folder 29 / 9-10)
  - Burton K. Wheeler presidential candidacy, 1940 (Box-folder 29 / 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940 (Box-folder 29 / 13-14)
  - Miscellaneous (includes accusations of mail fraud), 1941-1942 (Box-folder 29 / 15)
  - Miscellaneous (includes accusations of mail fraud), 1943-1944 (Box-folder 30 / 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box-folder 30 / 2)
  - Burton K. Wheeler senate campaign, 1946 (Box-folder 30 / 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1946-1972 (Box-folder 30 / 4-9)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 30 / 10-11)
  - Scrapbook re LaFollette-Wheeler campaign, 1924 (Box-folder 31 / 1)
  - Scrapbook re LaFollette-Wheeler campaign, 1924 (Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook re Wheeler political activities and indictment, 1924-1925 (Box-folder 31 / 2)
  - Scrapbook re reorganization of Supreme Court, 1937 (Volume 2)
  - Scrapbook "From the Detroit Chapter of the America First Committee, 'The Vietigs'", 1941 (Box-folder 31 / 3)
  - Scrapbook re Yankee from the West, 1962 (Volume 3)
- Audio Recordings
  - Untitled, Undated (Box-folder Media Cabinet)
  - Untitled, Undated (Box-folder Media Cabinet)
  - Untitled, Undated (Box-folder Media Cabinet)
  - B. K. Wheeler Speech, American Neutrality, circa 1940 (Box-folder Media Cabinet)
  - B. K. Wheeler Speech, American Neutrality, circa 1940 (Box-folder Media Cabinet)
  - B. K. Wheeler Speech, American Neutrality, circa 1940 (Box-folder Media Cabinet)
  - B. K. Wheeler Speech, American Neutrality, circa 1940 (Box-folder Media Cabinet)